A 13,000 mile dragon of earth and stone
winds /曲折而行/ its way through
the countryside of China
with a history almost as long
and serpentine /ˈsɜːpənˌtaɪn 蜿蜒的/ as the structure.
The Great Wall began as multiple walls
of rammed /ræm 夯实的/ earth
built by individual feudal /ˈfjuːdəl 封建时代的/ states
during the Chunqiu period
to protect against nomadic /nəʊˈmædɪk 游牧的/ raiders /ˈreɪdə 侵入者/
north of China and each other.
When Emperor Qin Shi Huang
unified /ˈjuːnɪˌfaɪ 统一/ the states in 221 BCE,
the Tibetan /tɪˈbetən/ Plateau /ˈplætəʊ 高原/ and Pacific Ocean
became natural barriers /ˈbærɪə 屏障/,
but the mountains in the north
remained vulnerable
to Mongol /ˈmɒŋɡɒl/, Turkish /ˈtɜːkɪʃ/, and Xiongnu invasions.
To defend against them,
the Emperor expanded the small walls
built by his predecessors /ˈpriːdɪˌsɛsə 前任，前辈/,
connecting some and fortifying /ˈfɔːtɪˌfaɪ 加固/ others.
As the structures grew
from Lintao in the west
to Liaodong in the east,
they collectively became known
as The Long Wall.
To accomplish this task,
the Emperor enlisted /ɪnˈlɪst 征募/ soldiers /ˈsəʊldʒə/
and commoners /ˈkɒmənə 平民/,
not always voluntarily /ˈvɒləntərɪlɪ 志愿地/.
Of the hundreds of thousands of builders
recorded during the Qin Dynasty,
many were forcibly /fɔ:səbli 强制地/ conscripted /ˈkɒnskrɪpt 征召/ peasants /ˈpezənt 农夫/
and others were criminals
serving out sentences.
Under the Han Dynasty,
the wall grew longer still,
reaching 3700 miles,
and spanning /spæn/ from Dunhuang
to the Bohai Sea.
Forced labor continued
under the Han Emperor Han-Wudi ,
and the walls reputation grew
into a notorious /nəʊˈtɔːrɪəs 臭名昭著的/ place of suffering.
Poems and legends of the time
told of laborers buried /ˈberɪ/
in nearby mass /mæs/ graves /ɡreɪv 坟/,
or even within the wall itself.
And while no human remains
have been found inside,
grave pits /pɪt 坑/ do indicate /ˈɪndɪˌkeɪt 指示/
that many workers died
from accidents, hunger and exhaustion.
The wall was formidable /fɔːˈmɪdəbəl 令人生畏/
but not invincible /ɪnˈvɪnsɪbəl 不可战胜/.
Both Genghis and his son Khublai Khan
managed to surmount /sɜːˈmaʊnt 攻克/ the wall
during the Mongol invasion
of the 13th Century.
After the Ming dynasty
gained control in 1368,
they began to refortify /riːˈfɔːtɪˌfaɪ 使再加固/
and further consolidate /kənˈsɒlɪˌdeɪt 加强/ the wall
using bricks and stones from local kilns /kɪln 窑,炉/.
Averaging /平均/ 23 feet high and 21 feet wide,
the walls 5500 miles
were punctuated /ˈpʌŋktjʊˌeɪt 不时打断/ by watchtowers.
When raiders /ˈreɪdə 侵入者/ were sighted,
fire and smoke signals traveled
between towers
until reinforcements /援军/ arrived.
Small openings along the wall
let archers /ˈɑːtʃə 弓箭手/ fire on invaders,
while larger ones were used
to drop stones and more.
But even this new and improved wall
was not enough.
In 1644, northern Manchu clans /klæn 部落/
overthrew /ˌəʊvəˈθrəʊ 推翻/ the Ming
to establish the Qing dynasty,
incorporating Mongolia as well,
Thus, for the second time,
China was ruled by the very people
the wall had tried to keep out.
With the empire's /ˈɛmpaɪə 帝国/ borders
now extending beyond the Great Wall,
the fortifications /ˌfɔːtɪfɪˈkeɪʃən 防御工事/ lost their purpose.
And without regular reinforcement,
the wall fell into disrepair /失修/,
rammed /ræm 夯实/ earth eroded /ɪˈrəʊd 腐蚀/,
while brick and stone were plundered /ˈplʌndə 掠夺/
for building materials.
But its job wasn't finished.
During World War II,
China used sections for defense
against Japanese invasion,
and some parts are still rumored /ˈruːmə 谣言/
to be used for military training.
But the Wall's main purpose
today is cultural.
As one of the largest man-made
structures on Earth,
it was granted UNESCO
World Heritage /ˈher.ɪ.tɪdʒ 遗产/ Status in 1987.
Originally built to keep
people out of China,
the Great Wall now welcomes
millions of visitors each year.
In fact, the influx /ˈɪnˌflʌks 涌入/ of tourists
has caused the wall to deteriorate /dɪˈtɪərɪəˌreɪt 恶化/,
leading the Chinese government
to launch preservation /ˌprɛzəˈveɪʃən 保存/ initiatives /ɪˈnɪʃɪətɪv 主动性/ .
It's also often acclaimed /əˈkleɪm 称赞/ as the only
man-made structure visible from space.
Unfortunately, that's not at all true.
In low Earth orbit /ˈɔːbɪt/,
all sorts of structures,
like bridges, highways
and airports are visible,
and the Great Wall
is only barely /ˈbɛəlɪ 几乎不/ discernible /dɪˈsɜːnəbəl 看得清的/.
From the moon, it doesn't stand a chance /有机会/.
But regardless, it's the Earth
we should be studying it from
because new sections
are still discovered every few years,
branching /brɑːntʃ 分支/ off from the main body
and expanding this remarkable
monument /ˈmɒnjʊmənt 纪念碑 遗迹/ to human achievement.